<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: musings | Deep Musings]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/categories/musings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.deepmusings.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-23T13:16:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.deepmusings.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Bhavdeep Sethi]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[bhavdeep_sethi@yahoo.in]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's just live for today!]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2014/04/25/lets-just-live-for-today/"/>
        <updated>2014-04-25T18:42:32-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2014/04/25/lets-just-live-for-today</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m don&#8217;t know the actual source of this poem so can&#8217;t give proper credit for this. If you know where this verse is from, please reach out to me so I can link the source.  </p>




<p><em><br />
Before the world validates our identity based on race &amp; creed,<br />
Before they tell us where we belong &amp; which air we ought to breathe,<br />
For now, for once, let&#8217;s just live for today!</p>


<p>Before life drags us apart and tries molding our fate,<br />
</p>


<p></em></p>

<!--more-->


<p><em>
Before fanaticism conquers love &amp; our credibility is put on stake,<br />
For now, for once, let&rsquo;s just live for today!</p>

<p>Before the night looses its charm &amp; the moon hides &amp; fades,<br />
Before the first gleam of sunshine makes them discover our shade,<br />
For now, for once, let&#8217;s just live for today!</p>


<p>Before social apprehensions make us kneel &amp; break,<br />
Before we&#8217;re made to choose between the obvious &amp; man-made,<br />
For now, for once, let&#8217;s just live for today!<br />
</em></p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three most significant things you have learnt till date]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2014/02/22/three-most-significant-things-you-have-learnt-till-date/"/>
        <updated>2014-02-22T18:27:28-05:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2014/02/22/three-most-significant-things-you-have-learnt-till-date</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Write down the three most significant things you have learnt till date.</h3>




<p>I had to answer this question recently and I realized how different life experiences reflect on your views. I asked some of my friends this question and it was really interesting to hear what others had to say. Some said things that were relevant to them at that moment of time, some shared their long held beliefs. Knowingly or unknowingly they share something that defines them. You&#8217;ll probably end up learning something about yourself as well.  </p>


<p>So, now, I ask you to answer the same question. What are the three most significant things you have learnt till date? Make sure that you don&#8217;t spend too much time thinking about it. Just list out down the top three things that you can think of. You can then elaborate on why you think you chose these. </p>


<p>By the way, here were my answers: </p>


<p><strong>#1 Always listen to your heart. It&#8217;ll lead you the right way. </strong><br />
<span id="more-263"></span></p>


<!--more-->


<p>Post under-graduation, I had offers from Infosys and TCS, two of the biggest IT companies in India. I joined Infosys based on the feedback I got from my seniors. Having excelled in their training program, they decided to place me in a department called LERN. Infosys was entering into the e-learning market, a $50 Billion industry, which is likely to double in size before 2015. They needed sharp folks who could translate technically challenging material into easy to understand workflows. One caveat though, the job did not require any coding, just using some tools. They pick their best programmers and put them in a department which needed zero programming skills. Ironic? Tell me about it. I obviously asked for a department change, but they said it couldn&#8217;t be done for at least a year. Oh, and Infosys had made us sign a contract that would enforce a monetary fine in case I leave the company before completing a year. They were asking for more money than they had actually paid me till that time. Along with this, the HRs were using lots of legal jargon to make sure I did not leave. I did not know anybody who had left before completing a year, so I didn&#8217;t know how to proceed ahead.
</p>


<p>I knew one thing though. The few months spent there were depressing. The work life was mediocre. It was not challenging enough. It was not something I wanted to do. This in turn was taking a toll on my personal life as well. Misunderstandings, arguments… and the whole nine yards were getting regular with friends. After one of such days, I realized that no amount of money was worth this. I decided I had to leave right then. I didn&#8217;t know what I was going to do next. I was ready to work for absolutely no salary at all. I just wanted to do some good work. With only the belief in my ability to make /something/ out of this situation, I decided to leave Infosys and join a startup (MIME360). This, obviously did not go down well with friends and family. I was leaving a stable job with a reputed IT giant  to work in a company incubating in college with 6 employees. Startups weren&#8217;t a big deal in India back then (still aren&#8217;t, but things are changing fast) so it was difficult to explain to people the rationale behind the move. I stuck to my decision, sorted out my priorities and was ready to face whatever came next. Eventually, Flipkart.com, the biggest eCommerce company in India, acquired MIME360 to build its digital arm. And I&#8217;ve never looked back since. <img src="http://www.deepmusings.com/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif" alt=":)" class="wp-smiley" />
</p>


<p>
Considering we spend one third of our life working, make sure you love what you&#8217;re doing.
</p>


<p><strong>#2 Hard work beats Talent when talent doesn&#8217;t work hard.</strong></p>


<p>At Flipkart, I got the opportunity to work with some of the best brains in the country. I was surrounded by people from premier institutions like IIT, BITS, NIT, IIIT, etc., while I was from a simple college from a simple university. I had heard a lot of hype about performance levels of individuals from these colleges. I realize that&#8217;s exactly what it was. Pure hype. So you were a topper of Computer Science department? Congrats! This might help you get into the company, however, this matters very little in real life. Most of the challenges we face are new so, past laurels don&#8217;t matter much. What matters is how much effort you can put into a task and your ability to get things done. You have to constantly keep learning and keep up with technology. If you love what you do and work with dedication, you&#8217;ll never stop growing, both personally and professionally. And soon, people will recognize and respect what you add to the team, regardless of your background. </p>


<p><strong>#3 Time heals almost everything. Give time, time. </strong></p>


<p>This might be a little personal but it resonates with me very strongly. Like everybody, I&#8217;ve seen lots of ups and downs in my life (Yes, I also realize, at 25, I&#8217;ve not seen anything yet). But what has worked for me is I tend to stick with problems longer. If you want things to work out, sometimes you&#8217;ll have to give it time. Healing doesn&#8217;t take a day. It takes a lot of little steps to get back. Eventually everything falls into place. It might not be how you pictured it, it might not even work in your favor, but over the long run, you&#8217;ll realize that it&#8217;s actually better this way. In the end, it&#8217;s about patience, perseverance and persistence. Do not give up. </p>


<hr />




<p><font color="#1F7DE0"><u><i>Update</i></u></font> : I asked the same question on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news" title="HN" target="_blank">HN</a>. Here are some gems <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7281635" title="Ask HN" target="_blank">from that post</a> in no particular order: </p>


<ul>
<li> Don&#8217;t be too hard on yourselves. You tend to make mistakes, and there is no way to become better without making them. Put the past behind and move on. Easier said than done, though.</li>
<li> Failure is the default state of any venture. Give your best to succeed, but remember that you&#8217;re starting from failure. This way, you learn to handle the lows associated with failures better.</li>
<li> Focus on the process as much as on the results. The idea is to master the process that&#8217;s expected to return results so that you can keep using it to succeed at various things. </li>
<li> Opportunity Cost: Everything has a cost. Everything. At a minimum, it is the foregone time you could have invested into other activities rather than the thing that you&#8217;ve chosen to invest time in. Even if you had unlimited funds, you still have to chose what to do with your time, and that&#8217;s frighteningly finite. Realize, therefore, that you are always giving up something, and choosing to be weak in one area in return for being strong in another. No one is good at everything. No one has it all.</li>
<li> Labor-elasticity relative to wages/money can be negative, and that&#8217;s ok. For those not keyed in on economic mumbo-jumbo, that simply means that having more money can result in people choosing to work less. First year economics people (and i&#8217;m assuming many young, and HN-types) assume that everyone will do more work for more money. But money is not the point, and unless you&#8217;re neurotic and insecure (and most people who chase money are), there comes a time when you realise that maybe now that you&#8217;ve got money, you can instead use it on the things that really matter rather than trying to get more of it. And work, on the whole, is not the shit that matters&#8230;</li>
<li> Be humble and self-critical. Humble to realise how fallible and pathetically human you are, so that you don&#8217;t beat yourself or others up too much, and how much luck had to do with any success that comes your way, and how much it has to do with a great deal of suffering that comes the way of others. Self-critical so you can deal with, improve upon and compensate for the flaws you realise you have.</li>
<li>Spend more money on experiences and less on things.</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t dread potentially poor outcomes because they are never as bad as they seem. </li>
<li>Competence, confidence, and efficiency go a long way.</li>
<li> Think bigger. Work on ambitious projects. You become what you spend your time on. And big visions attract money and talent. Think bigger.</li>
<li> Life is short, so make sure you&#8217;ll have no regrets when you die</li>
<li> Whether you think you can or can&#8217;t, you&#8217;re right </li>
<li> Foolish decisions are often the ones you regret the less </li>
<li>Work hard. Be strong. Don&#8217;t complain.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Inspiring Commencement Speeches]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2013/08/17/some-inspiring-commencement-speeches/"/>
        <updated>2013-08-17T20:30:13-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.deepmusings.com/blog/2013/08/17/some-inspiring-commencement-speeches</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>David Foster Wallace 2005 Kenyon College Commencement Speech - This is Water.</h3>


<p>By far one of the best commencement speech ever. It talks about something so basic, yet something so profound that it makes you wonder how cluelessly you&#8217;ve been living your life.</p>


<p>The speech has been turned into a book as well:</p>


<p>http://www.amazon.com/This-Water-Delivered-Significant-Compassionate/dp/0316068225/</p>


<p>Link to the full speech:</p>


<p><iframe width="584" height="438" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/IYGaXzJGVAQ?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>


<p>Here is a beautiful visual excerpt of the same video:<br />
<a title="This Is Water - Visual Excerpt" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DaVrn1Sz0H8" target="_blank">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DaVrn1Sz0H8</a></p>


<p>I don&#8217;t think I&#8217;ll do justice summarizing this speech. Just quoting the statements I found most profound.</p>


<p>The most obvious realities are most often the ones that are hardest to see and talk about. If you are automatically sure that you know what reality is, who and what is really important; if you want to operate on your default setting, then you, like me, will not consider possibilities that are not annoying and miserable.<br />
If you really learn how to think, how to pay attention, then you&#8217;ll know you have other options.<br />
You get to consciously decide what has meaning and what doesn&#8217;t. That is real freedom. That is being educated and understanding how to think.<br />
The real value of real education which has almost nothing to do with knowledge and everything to do with simple awareness. Awareness of what is so real and essential, so hidden in plain sight all around us all the time that we have to keep reminding ourselves over and over. <strong>This is Water.</strong></p>


<hr />


<h3>Steve Jobs, Stanford 2005</h3>


<p>Very very inspiring. Three big take aways from this speech:</p>


<!--more-->


<p><span id="more-67"></span><br />
1) Follow your heart.</p>


<p>So you have to trust that the dots will connect in future. Because believing that the dots will connect down the road will give you the confidence to follow your heart even when it leads you off the well worn path and that will make all the difference.</p>


<p>2) Love and loss.</p>


<p>Sometimes life is gonna hit you in the head with a brick. Don&#8217;t lose faith.<br />
The only thing that will keep you going is to love what you do. If you haven&#8217;t found it yet, then keep looking. Don&#8217;t settle.</p>


<p>3) Death</p>


<p>Remembering that I’ll be dead soon is the most important tool I’ve ever encountered to help me make the big choices in life. Because almost everything — all external expectations, all pride, all fear of embarrassment or failure – these things just fall away in the face of death, leaving only what is truly important. Remembering that you are going to die is the best way I know to avoid the trap of thinking you have something to lose. You are already naked. There is no reason not to follow your heart.</p>


<p>Your time is limited, so don&#8217;t waste it living someone else&#8217;s life. Don&#8217;t be trapped by dogma — which is living with the results of other people&#8217;s thinking. Don&#8217;t let the noise of others&#8217; opinions drown out your own inner voice. And most important, have the courage to follow your heart and intuition. They somehow already know what you truly want to become. Everything else is secondary.</p>


<p>Link to the full speech:</p>


<p><iframe width="584" height="438" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/UF8uR6Z6KLc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>


<hr />


<h3>Jeff Bezos&#8217;s Princeton Commencement Speech</h3>


<p>Bezos spoke to the Class of 2010 about the difference between choices and gifts. Cleverness, Bezos pointed out, is a gift, while being kind to others is a choice. One&#8217;s character, he suggested, is reflected not in the gifts one is endowed with at birth but rather by the choices one makes over the course of a lifetime.</p>


<p>Ponder over these:</p>


<ul>
<li>How will you use your gifts? What choices will you make?</li>
<li>Will inertia be your guide, or will you follow your passions?</li>
<li>Will you follow dogma, or will you be original?</li>
<li>Will you choose a life of ease, or a life of service and adventure?</li>
<li>Will you wilt under criticism, or will you follow your convictions?</li>
<li>Will you bluff it out when you&#8217;re wrong, or will you apologize?</li>
<li>Will you guard your heart against rejection, or will you act when you fall in love?</li>
<li>Will you play it safe, or will you be a little bit swashbuckling?</li>
<li>When it&#8217;s tough, will you give up, or will you be relentless?</li>
<li>Will you be a cynic, or will you be a builder?</li>
<li>Will you be clever at the expense of others, or will you be kind?</li>
</ul>


<p>Full link to the speech:</p>


<p><iframe width="584" height="438" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/vBmavNoChZc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>


<hr />


<h3>JK Rowling, Harvard 2008</h3>


<p>Two main themes of her extremely witty speech were<br />
1) Failure -<br />
Failure is a very liberating experience. It is the stripping of the inessentials. Hitting rock bottom, you realize that you can survive anything now. You understand that your qualifications and your CVs are not your life.</p>


<p>2) Imagination/Empathy<br />
We are bound to touch other people&#8217;s lives simply by existing. So let ua use our abilities to help the less fortunate. We do not need magic to transform our world. We carry all the power we need inside ourselves already.</p>


<p>Link to the full speech:</p>


<p><iframe width="584" height="438" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/wHGqp8lz36c?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>


<hr />


<h3>Randy Pausch&#8217;s Last Lecture: Achieving Your Childhood Dreams</h3>


<p>Even though this is not a commencement speech, it deserves a special mention. It&#8217;s a thought provoking, truly inspiring lecture. Here are some gems from this video:</p>


<ul>
<li>We cannot change the cards we&#8217;re dealt, just how we play the hand.</li>
<li>The brick walls are there for a reason. The brick walls are not there to keep us out. The brick walls are there for us to show how badly we want something.</li>
<li>Never lose the childlike wonder.</li>
<li>Help Others.</li>
<li>Loyalty is a two-way street.</li>
<li>Never give up.</li>
<li>Tell the truth.</li>
<li>Be earnest.</li>
<li>Apologize when you screw up.</li>
<li>Focus on others, not yourself.</li>
<li>Get a feedback loop and listen to it.</li>
<li>Show gratitude.</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t complain, just work harder.</li>
<li>Be good at something, it makes you valuable.</li>
<li>Find the best in everybody, no matter how long you have to wait for them to show it.</li>
<li>Be prepared. &#8220;Luck&#8221; is where preparation meets opportunity.</li>
</ul>


<p>Link to the full speech:</p>


<p><iframe width="584" height="438" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/ji5_MqicxSo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>


<hr />


<p>Which are your favorite commencement speeches? Or which talks/videos do you find highly inspirational? Let me know!</p>

]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
