<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hackers | Deep Musings]]></title>
  <link href="http://bhavdeepsethi.github.io/blog/categories/hackers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bhavdeepsethi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-10T00:56:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bhavdeepsethi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bhavdeep Sethi]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[bhavdeep_sethi@yahoo.in]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from WordPress to Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://bhavdeepsethi.github.io/blog/2014/12/11/moving-from-wordpress-to-github/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T21:03:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bhavdeepsethi.github.io/blog/2014/12/11/moving-from-wordpress-to-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>
So&hellip;the look and feel of the blog changed. For the good, I hope! Basically my GoDaddy webhosting expired and they deleted all the content that was hosted on it. Uh&hellip;yeah, I know.:/</p>

<p><p><em>Luckily</em>, I had enabled the SuperCache Plugin on WordPress. Along with the Backup to DropBox Plugin, I was able to retrieve some of the posts. I&rsquo;m getting into the writing mode again and not to mention that a lot has happened in the past six months&hellip;so I decided to revive the blog. The fact that I had to get involved with WordPress and GoDaddy again had already kept me away from this task for so long. <br /></p>

<p>But not anymore!
<!--more-->
I randomly googled &ldquo;<a href="http://goo.gl/02SPK4">blogging platform for coders</a>&rdquo;, went to the HN link from the result and read about Jekyll+Github. And I can&rsquo;t believe I hadn&rsquo;t heard about this for so long!  I was aware that you could create simple pages for your projects but when I saw what I could actually do (with User and Project pages both), I regretted not looking around for more options earlier. <br /></p>

<p>With Octopress into the picture, you do not even have to bother with the blog structure/theme. It took me about half a day to migrate the entire blog. Or whatever was left of it.</p>

<p><p><h3>Why GitHub User Pages are way better than WordPress for your blog?</h3>
<ul>
<li>The power of Github! You can add collaborators, markdowns, issue tracking, versioning&hellip;do I need to say more?
<li> You can write articles using your everyday IDE! Intellij/Sublime Text FTW!
<li>You own the code. You decide how the code is going to be rendered. In WordPress(WP), you ended up writing articles and having no control of what is going on behind the scene. It took me three days to get a simple jQuery functionality working with WP.
<li> You can run your blog locally. Making changes is so much faster. I can work on the blog even when I don&rsquo;t have an internet connection.<br/>
<li> I prefer working on the command line. Period. Navigating along the blog like you would ssh&#8217;ing into a webserver is so much faster than being forced to use a horrible GUI. And yes, MySQL CLI &gt;&gt;&gt; MySQL Workbench.
<li>With your blog being hosted on Github, you treat it as an everyday project! Publishing a new post is no longer a hassle!
</ul>
<br />
I could go on and on&hellip;but you get the picture. I am so glad I moved to this new platform. It feels like home here. :P</p>

<p><p> For others, who are considering this move, I strongly encourage it! The Octopress <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">Get Started guide</a> is all you need to get rolling! You can look at <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes" >this Github repo</a> to go through some of the user made themes. <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages/" >This Github Help</a> page will give you steps for setting up a custom domain with your github page. That&rsquo;s it! Seriously. You&rsquo;re done! Hope to see you on this side.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
